hi uh I'm just trying to get high enough
that the people in the back can
see because I hate to see people going
like
um
so I don't know I
started people started asking me to
teach around the time I finished my
gradate degree 1995 in New York and uh
people asked me in New York if I would
teach them what I learned in the
monastery you know the G program so in
in the monastery it takes 20 25
years and uh we studi very difficult
textbooks uh which are not available in
English hardly available into
Latin uh and
um so I undertook I think we started in
93 in New York and and I and I tried to
translate the most important parts of
the gashi course and um teach them for
the first time to to Western people
especially women there there weren't any
g g women into the nowadays there are a
few in darala just starting um but um so
I thought it would be nice if if a group
of people especially lay people you know
uh could uh Master the gashi course
which is quite difficult and then it
would be nice if they could pass it on
if those women uh and Men could become
teachers uh you know blame people
especially
because I don't think monasticism is is
going to catch on in America big uh and
maybe it's better that it doesn't uh I
think uh if people
could uh in their own homes and in their
own jobs uh
exemplify uh the high ideals of Buddhism
then that would be fine and if lay
people very well trained l people could
pass it on it would be very beautiful so
I taught 18 courses in New York uh we
translated about 10,000 pages of
text and it was beautiful and and a nice
uh crop was
harvested uh then I went into a
three-year Retreat and and when I came
out uh people asked me would you do the
same for the higher teachings of
Buddhism uh the secret teachings called
Diamond way
vajana so then uh I helped start D
mountain university near Tucson and we
undertook a course of uh study six or
seven years 18 courses of uh the secret
teachings of Buddhism and so the kids
graduated last
June uh and I think we've been very
lucky I know friend Dian was in the
first class in
1993 uh she hasn't missed one I think
but she missed one
class out of many hundreds of classes
uh so there are people here who survive
the whole thing and uh we are lucky I
think to have been able to complete such
a such a grand uh you know
undertaking as to train a bunch of
people in the gashi course and then do
the whole secret teachings so we we
finished uh we graduated 134 people uh
graduated last June uh then I became
unemployed you see
uh and uh I was casting about for things
to do with
myself uh because you know my idea is
you train the students to be teachers
and it's it's not my intention to just
redo all those courses I I would rather
that the students become the teachers
and teach them you know so I think a
good piano teacher makes themselves
Superfluous right uh and the students
play concerts and that's fine um but
then I thought that would be boring
so uh there's one beautiful beautiful
teaching that I was granted uh by my
teacher uh over the course of over 20
years and that's uh that's a book called
a gift of Liberation thrust into the
palm of your hands okay it's called
number L and it's a very beautiful uh
teaching uh it's 800 pages
long um it takes about you know it took
him him each each time he taught it took
about 8 years and uh it's a very very
beautiful uh book I was sitting in a
group of people the other day and we
were having lunch together and everybody
said what's your favorite book of all
time you know and somebody's said gone
with a what no to kill a I don't know
anyway we were going around and I said
oh no
num is the best book in the world you
know it's the most amazing book in the
world I love books and I spent my whole
life uh translating and studying books
there are 200,000 Tibetan
Classics uh but this one I think is the
greatest you know this book I think is
the greatest so then um I thought uh
since my own llama spent so many years
to load me with that teaching that it
would be remiss if I didn't unload it in
to some other people uh who could pass
it on you know so my dream the reason
I'm sitting here is that my dream is
that you are sitting here uh in the Next
Generation okay which could be 6 months
from now or or six weeks from now that
you start teaching what you have learned
each time to other people my fondest
hope and my dream is that uh you you
pass this teaching on to other people
it's a very very beautiful teaching and
it would make a person's life uh perfect
uh if you study this teaching and if you
learn it well then uh all these
beautiful things come to you beautiful
beautiful dreams beyond your beyond what
you can even imagine you know people
talk about angels coming to you and you
know having visions and and being really
really happy all the time
uh this book can can do that this is
what this book is if you study it uh
well it contains all the essence of the
gashi course and in the secret teachings
it's so the last 36 courses or the last
12 what is it 12,000 pages of
translation we've done it can all be
learned in this one book you know and in
a very gentle and beautiful way uh it's
a very very beautiful teaching
so my dream is uh that we could get
together twice a year like this and do
10 days like this and work through that
book my idea is that um we do 10 days
teaching uh the theory of the book and
then there's a tradition into B called
uhii means uh all the people who study
this particular book they go out in the
forest some together and they meditate
together for you know 10 days and they
try
to gain an inner experience of all the
of all the knowledge in the book you see
so in this uh particular style of
teaching this particular subject there's
a tradition that you you know we're
going to undertake 10 days of
explanation and you're going to do
homeworks and all this weird stuff and
by the way why
homeworks just so you can teach it
responsibly later okay it's I want you
to teach it responsibly you know I don't
want uh I have a mechanic working on my
car right now he didn't study very well
and uh he breaks it every week and I
take it back every week and then you
know to deal with people's Souls is a
little more serious than a Volvo a 1980
Volvo so uh you are dealing with
people's lives and I think it's you have
to I ask you to do the homeworks okay
and there will be they're easy homeworks
okay I I I made them short because this
is going to be intense this will be a an
intense time we won't have a lot of free
time so then you will uh it'll be a
pretty easy homework and and I'm I'm
asking you after each night that you do
the homework the idea on the homework is
that you you cheat and you do it with
somebody else
okay so I'm asking you to do the
homework with with at least one other
person in this room okay and hopefully
someone you don't already know so that's
why you have these stupid name types on
okay so you're supposed to during the
break which will be
shortly uh not too shortly but during
the break you will go up to somebody you
know that you're Milling around next to
the refreshment table and you'll say you
know do you want to get together and
work on homewor together we've arranged
uh the nearest Paradise Cafe and Bakery
which is the address is on your sheet or
something but there will be uh gangs of
people there uh whenever we're not here
okay so they can sit and help you with
your homework they have the answer keys
you get the answer keys after the class
is over okay so that you can teach from
the ENT Keys all right so there will be
uh teaching assistants Tas at Paradise
Cafe just paradise and uh and then you
just if you want to go there and hang
out and do your homework with other
people but what I really want is that
people sit and talk with each other and
you say I didn't I was kind of nodding
off when he was talking about this and
do you remember what he said and the see
I was nodding off too cuz I flew in from
New York and it was 3 hours later from
me too and there'll probably be one
person in the group who was awake and uh
my home then then you sit and do the
homework together okay I really want
that and I want you to meet people you
don't know okay so don't hang out in
little clicks of D mountain or a New
York or Lake Tahoe people you know like
try to talk to somebody else all right
it'll be fun what happens is you end up
teaching in Argentina or something with
them you know like they know yoga and
you know M and you know they need
somebody it happens it's happened a lot
so please do the homework uh there'll be
a certificate at the end certificate
means you finished all the homeworks you
attended all the
classes uh and I feel that that you
could teach it to somebody else all
right and that means you'll have to
catch all the classes if if you have to
be away for one class or two classes
like you can't get here on Tuesday night
or Thursday night uh like you're
from I don't know Taiwan there's people
in Shanghai you got to go back to
Shanghai during the week I don't know
but um or Norway wherever you are uh
then you can catch those two classes
there's supposed to be a live streaming
video and and there's also a video we'll
store it online and you can get it and
then you catch up if you catch up and do
your homework then then still you can
get a certificate okay but I would like
to hand out certificates and I would
like to people who have them could then
teach other people right teach other
people what
uh this whole text okay this is the I
was honored enough to borrow my
teacher's copy uh this is k r copy and
uh so as you can see it's kind of fat
and uh it's going to take us 10 years to
finish I I count it uh it's
20 courses like this okay uh over the
next 10 years I I think it's a really
nice Fine Thing I think we will bond and
I think uh you know we will get together
twice a year and have this kind of
theory course and then twice a year
we'll do a 10-day Retreat okay and and
Rebecca has been uh where is she she's
she's managed to find a really nice
place in Prescott Arizona uh we weren't
sure if 10 people would sign up or 50 so
we got a place that fit
120 and we're
booked uh but we're trying to make it
bigger she's working on the walls and
we're asking people to eat not so much
before uh but anyway my dream is that uh
20 times we will meet in the next 10
years uh for this uh course and then 20
times we will go on a
retreat and and it's so beautiful and so
powerful to study an authentic beautiful
well preserved tradition
on meditation for example get it from a
person who got it from you know one of
the last great llamas
ofet and then
uh and then do a retreat you know uh in
silence together on that and it's very
powerful it's really really beautiful
and I think I hope I believe it will
make your life very happy for the next
10 years okay uh it will make you very
happy just you it's like I feel like
it's going back to a gas station every
few months so every 3 4 months you you
will come back for
gas uh from the text and and we'll do
the next great subject and as
you learn and then meditate your heart
will change and your life will change
and wonderful beautiful amazing things
will happen to you and and your life
will be will just be like a dream you
know and like a like an incred dream
that you could never imagine so I I feel
like very strongly I feel like this is a
that some Karma has brought us all
together tonight you know like I don't
even know a lot of you very well and but
some Karma has brought us to be together
tonight and we we will be together for a
while uh and we will do some very
beautiful thing together and and in the
process your life will start to change
radically uh what the courses we did
before were sort of Advanced Analytical
courses and this one is a very strong
powerful heart course and it changes
your heart and it changes your life and
it's very very beautiful I was reading
it and I was so happy that we're going
to do this thing together okay
so without more Ado right without
further Ado we'll start we have to keep
on a pretty tight schedule to make it in
10 years
I'm not kidding I figured it all out so
we have to go pretty well I'm going to
do the old you know the old
way uh the old Tibetan way which I don't
get to do much because I'm always have
to do business seminars and partner
seminars and all this stuff so uh I I I
just like to do it the old way I will
read the D sentence and then I'll
explain it to you and uh it will also be
a l l means uh the teacher gives an oral
transmission of the text which they have
received uh in whole from their teachers
so I received this teaching three
times uh from K my teacher and
um so I have all the words in me somehow
okay and then I will somehow give them
to you and then you can pass it on all
right so you have to listen when I read
the to that it's a it's the blessing of
a thousand years of transmission okay so
then take it in you you know never go
from
there so this text is called uh ready oh
I was going to do one thing now I'll do
it at the end right I always do out of
order can we start the the tietan text
are you ready are you going to
scroll
okay I'm just going to put the the text
up there you don't have to read it you
know I don't care about it much okay
those of you who know Tibetan or want to
know the Tibetan uh you can
follow the uh
the Tibetan text but other rest of you
don't worry about it okay you're not
going to teach it in Tibetan or
Latin uh you're going to teach it in in
your mother tongue whatever it is okay
so this that's just for the benefit of
the people who want to learn into them
so the the first line there is the title
and it
says uh this book ined is called n
please say
N N means Liberation okay and we'll talk
about what kinds of
liberation you can say reaching a
mandala or reaching I got it over
here uh reaching a holy mandala okay
reaching a a paradise in this world okay
L Chang is very beautiful
L there's no other book called that and
it's very unusual and it means the Llama
comes he says put out your hand put out
your hand just put out your hand for
good luck and then the teacher comes and
goes bam
there Liberation take it you know that's
number L okay so the name of the book is
Bam Liberation in the hand okay it just
means like they they translate all these
wiy translations I don't know it means a
gift of Liberation thrust into your
hands thrust into your outreached HS
okay it's very difficult to translate
okay like took this is a profound
instruction it is complete and it has no
error
it is without
equal it is the cream of the cream
within the holy heart of the king of the
Dharma
J
CH we have to talk about that okay CH
say Chu
CH I'm not saying that when you teach
this you have to say all this gibberish
okay and I'm not trying to confuse or
discourage people who are new okay I I
want you to know that it's authentic and
that has come from a tradition of
thousands it's this tradition is a lot
of men really started 2 and a half
thousand years ago so I I just want you
to know it's
authentic my dream now you can do the ba
thing you ready you you thought you I
was going to do that
right my dream is the following okay
where is
that we got this weird email uh like I
don't know 5 months ago
from uh British
Airways and you know this is A1 billion
company uh and they have 43,000
employees around the world and and so we
got this email and they said would you
come help us you know we we're having
financial difficulties we're having
labor disputes you know we would like to
see if your approach could help us in
our in our business you know and and
then uh we went they flew us to London I
don't know two months
agole weeks ago no I mean two months ago
they flew three of us to London two
months ago they had uh they had a 12 of
the senior people in the company like
people who run they each run 10,000
employees you know and then they said
you have one hour to convince us that
you can help us you know and and I gave
them number lock time in one hour you
know and we just gave them the beautiful
ideas and
and obviously in front of a group of
labor union tough guys and management
tough guys you can't get up and give
some new age you know Buddhist thing you
can't do that and it wouldn't be
appropriate they were
saying do you have ideas that could help
our company regardless of our
orientation you know like can you
present the ideas that you've learned
and that you speak about
can you present them in a way that A1
billion company could Implement them and
turn the company around you see and
that's my dream you see I would like to
see you take this Buddhist Tibetan
n long thing right and you study it well
and you digest it well and then you spit
it out as some kind of help for normal
people without the baggage okay got it
so you're going to I'm going to sit up
here and throw tobet words at you and
you're going to hear weird stories about
some Buddhist meditator from a thousand
years ago in K but what I dream of and
what I want is that over the coming
years you go to work you go to your
family you go to normal people like Ry
vice presidents and and you regurgitate
it just the ideas and not the religion
okay just the powerful
sweet uh what do you call
it they work you know ideas that can
change their company you know or change
a person's life or change a person's
marriage or change a person's you know
finances or their health you see can you
without the what do you call Tibetan
rigal which I'm giving you I want you to
leave it at the door when you leave the
church you know and then you just
bloated with these powerful beautiful
sweet ideas and practices we had all
those Executives in a retreat for three
days uh by the way this is at their
headquarters uh this is at the a anyway
so first we gave them two days of uh
just the ideas that could change their
company without any mention of Buddhism
or Tibet okay then we took the people
you got some of the
stuff uh yeah we then we took six people
over there they gave us 5 days with
their top people we took them out in the
British Countryside and we we drilled
them you know and we gave them yoga and
they did
meditation and then they had eight hours
of you know very powerful ideas for
their company yeah more uh Kevin came
he's good because he he speaks he grew
up in London uh Beth came
fantastic Scott
B and then oh that's
B uh that's Mercedes leading a breakout
group actually in another country but
that's okay uh
so uh but what happened was uh we we got
a letter from the vice president what
yesterday or the day before and they
said you know fantastic and they said
you know how can we now how can we make
this part of the culture of our company
without the baggage you know how can we
just take the sweet ideas and the sweet
ways of doing things different way of
doing things and make it part of our our
civilization that's my dream I want you
over the next 10 years to master this
thing and then I want you to take it to
the normal world and change the world
and I don't care if you don't have a
Buddha picture in your house or I don't
care if you can ring a bell or I don't
care if you know to that grammar it
doesn't matter to me at all okay I'm
going to use it because it's the
tradition but I want you to take it to
normal people and help them you see and
make them happy and isn't that the point
okay I don't I don't care if you know
the Tibetan grammar or not I'm going to
give it to you because it's the
tradition but I want you to give it and
change people make people happy okay
give people a really happy life and and
a really deep and beautiful and
meaningful life and they tasted it and
they got it you know these big big uh
executive they got a taste and they're
so excited and it's so fun you there's a
guy writing micans every day uh he's in
charge of All European operations
and thousands and thousands of employees
and he's like riding every day about the
cool stuff that's happening to him and
he's so happy you know and his life is
changing and that's what I really I want
you I want to load you with this stuff
and I want to see you at American
Airlines okay something like that I
probably there's some kind of non
competition thing for
me
okay so uh that's my dream I want you to
take it to the world use it in your
normal life how do you best affect other
people how do you best affect I went to
a teaching in Tucson his Holiness came
he taught uh Master Shanti deas chapter
on patience right and then he said are
there any questions and a friend of mine
raised her hand she has two at the time
she had two small children and she said
oh your Holiness you know how do we
teach these uh High ideas to our
children you know and he was like
M and then he said uh you can't talk to
them cuz they don't listen you know and
then he's like you know you just have to
be a good example you know like your
kids will do whatever you do no matter
what you say your kids will do what you
do and and it and it and my friend's
face fell uh because it was so difficult
it was such a difficult instruction you
know like you have to do it you have to
do what I'm teaching you and then your
children will learn from you from your
example what I'm asking is that as we go
through this book uh you master the way
of life and then you reflected in your
life and you become that way of life and
it's it's very beautiful there's a guy
named maroon right in Ireland do you
guys know him maroon right he's from
beut and uh he's married to an Irish
woman right and um he told me he was
driving me in the car not long ago and I
he said uh G you know my daughter asked
me why am I doing this meditation every
day uh she's how 10 or something at the
time so you know he said well honey um
I'm trying to be a better person and she
said well what what kind of better
person he said well I'm trying you know
how angry daddy used to be all the time
and yelling in the house and and I
decided to try to change myself and so
I'm meditating every day and and she
said said oh yes daddy and then then he
said have you seen me get angry in the
in the year that I've been meditating
you know and she said Daddy you haven't
been angry in in a year that you've been
meditating it's amazing now you're right
and then she said daddy do you have to
take a whole hour to get to
that but what I mean is the the child
changed right the child's life was
changed by her father's behavior and not
by his what he said right so I I hope
that you take this teaching and and
become it and that you teach by example
but it's also good to explain the book
too all right from from a point of view
of being an example both okay at the
same time all right now we'll start the
class and you're going to stay late
somehow you knew that all right we will
take a break right we have a break right
at some point I'll give you a
refreshment break okay so this book uh
is remember L and it means uh Liberation
thrust into your hands it is it is a l
Rim say l l l if you don't learn any
other word tonight you should go home
with L Rim say l r people remember this
word because it's one of the only tietan
words that you could pronounce in
English um so l means
path and rim means a step L Rim is a
style of of teaching that was actually
begun by Lord Buddha 2 and a half
thousand years
ago and it's an it's a what do you call
it Li it's Enlightenment for dummies
okay it's an Enlightenment for dummies
it it says step one do this step two do
this step three do this you get to step
21 you are in light you see it's like
fixing a car or something it's like a
manual for enlightenment just do these
things one by one then I teach you don't
ask questions you know just do one just
do two just do three by the time we get
to 25 you'll be enlightened okay and
it's very beautiful so this is a long
Rim steps of the path chongu means
Enlightenment
okay
means this teaching was given in
1921 okay in
1921 a Lama named pabona rep pabona p a
b o n g k a
Pon uh which is a long story but there's
a monastery near vas called
pong and and he he was the reincarnated
Lama of that Monastery uh long story so
Aon Imp in
1921 gave a teaching it was 24 days long
it was probably 8 to 12 hours a day and
uh 700 people came which inet was a lot
why in
1921 there was no microphones no
microphones okay uh so that was about
the max in a well-designed temple if you
scream you can 700 people can hear you
okay and then 700 people came he taught
for uh 24 days in a row and he went
through the whole steps of the path to
Enlightenment there was a 21y old
20-year-old precocious little
reincarnated tuu Lama
named do you have
pictures he was sitting in the audience
okay and
uh he's he's there yeah
that's
um he was sitting in the audience in
1921 he was 20 year old 20 years old and
he he decided he was going to be the
tape recorder right so he wrote down
notes he took down c means notes he took
down notes of the teaching and he
recorded the teaching then I think he
spent many many years of his life he
dedicated much of his life to cleaning
up those notes it was a thousand pages
of
notes and and he cleaned them up and
then he presented them to P do you have
a picture of
p
that's uh so he was born in 1878 and he
passed away in
1941 he gave this teaching he's the one
who gave this
teaching but this K can you show him
again he wrote it down and then uh later
he became the teacher of the Dal Lama
the Dal Lama was born in
1935 uh teacher R was already one of the
greatest llas of the country and they
asked him to be the D Lama's teacher all
right so he became the D's teacher he
also became my teacher's teacher you got
uh Ken
tou uh so T taught my teacher and he
taught the Dal Lama and then uh Ken is
the one who taught this to me so you are
now uh you're fourth generation right of
this teaching you're are the fourth
generation of this the structure of the
this L room is based on the one that
came from toaa who was
1357 you some no I didn't warn you did I
I did
yeah oh there you go that's J
Kaa uh he wrote one of these L teachings
back in
1409 or something and uh this book is
based on on his writing that's a real
image that was created during his
lifetime and and he design this kind of
teaching
okay and there's a very uh powerful
element which came from
Indonesia uh
Singa and that was brought to Tibet by a
llama Nam AA I think you have him and um
there's a very powerful element in he
designed the Lum that came into Tibet so
these are
the these are the people who from whom
this book has been passed down now
you're supposed to go through the manual
one by one from the beginning we're not
going to because we're Americans
okay so I thought let's start at the
back uh no because in the at the end of
the of this text uh they teach you how
to meditate okay but then they tell you
now go back and do the whole thing over
again with what we taught you about
meditation so I thought why not save you
some
time uh so we're going to do the section
on how to meditate
first because you're supposed to take
that
and then go study the rest of the steps
to Enlightenment you see so I I
thought let's give you that powerful
instrument called meditation
first combined with his teachings on
emptiness okay so you will go through
the whole steps to the path to
Enlightenment but you will be doing it
with these very powerful tools called
meditation and an understanding of how
we all Works a deep deep understanding
of how reality works why did British
Airways call
me uh the company I created to help the
devent refugees is the fastest growing
company in the history of New York City
I worked part I worked half
time uh and I always went home at five
you know and and the company was just
sold to Warr buffet for a quar billion
dollars okay 10,000 employees uh
uh and they were like how did you do
that and I said you have to understand
emptiness you know you just you learn to
meditate and you understand emptiness
and you can do anything you if you want
to make a big company you can make a big
company if you want to make a perfect
boyfriend you can make a perfect
boyfriend if you want to be healthy and
strong and young you can be healthy and
strong and young if you want to stop off
Afghanistan and stop Iraq and if you
want to see the world lifted out of
poverty and War you can do that too okay
but you have to understand emptiness you
can do anything if you understand
emptiness to understand emptiness you
have to learn to meditate so where are
we
starting we're starting with meditation
because you have to apply it to
emptiness and then I swear you can do
anything you want and people are
starting to believe it you know British
Airways called me because
they they're not quite sure okay but
they figure what the heck uh and they
said okay tell us how you did what you
did
and maybe we'll try it and they're
they're being actually very scientific
and very tough they they make us prove
everything they don't there there wasn't
a Buddhist in the room they don't care
about the Buddhist aspect they said uh
can you teach us to improve the
employees capacity of thinking and and
working out problems and can you give us
uh some insights that will help our
company make more money and also make
the employees more happy you see and and
what that means
is understanding how reality Works
understanding how the world works you
can only get to that if you can meditate
okay you can only learn that if you
meditate so we took them out in the
countryside we locked them into a room
and made them meditate you know and they
they're so happy uh they're really happy
so we have to start with meditation and
then we'll go
to how reality Works which reality means
companies your girlfriend your parents
your dog your boss you know your city
your country this is reality and and if
you learn to meditate you can unlock the
keys to those things and you can change
them and you can make the world a better
place okay you can fix the world you can
make the whole world happy if you
understand these things okay so we have
to start from meditation you have to
have a state of mind in which you can
you can understand how the world works
if you want to save the world
okay otherwise you're you're not helpful
you're not helping anybody okay so you
have to learn to meditate okay here we
go uh wait is there anything else on the
title that I didn't
[Music]
do
me
me inside this book is all the cream the
nectar of all the words of all the budas
D not these are hard advices D ningo is
the other name for this book which means
the essence of the nectar of
deathlessness that's the name of the
book okay I'm not making you memorize
the whole title which is that whole
thing all you have to do is say Liber a
gift of Liberation okay a gift of
Liberation here we go so we're skipping
to day number
21 on the 21st day
the
Lama
qued means the what do you call Regent
but next in line for the throne which
means the future Buddha whose name
is my okay and uh he's hanging out some
paradise and he's waiting to come down
the next Buddha is close Okay the next
Buddha in this world is very close Okay
and he
said uh
the mama quoted the coming who said
first you should go to a theoretical
class then you should go home and think
about what you learn in the theoretical
class and then you should when you've
taken it home and thought about
it you can go into a 10day retreat in
Prescott did you say
pres and and then you can grasp the
meaning of reality of how how the world
works and again I'm not saying something
in a cave okay I'm talking about
standing in the boardroom of a British
Airways and helping 43,000 workers okay
it's something you can do if you learn
this because they'll smell that you have
something okay got it they kept saying
we don't know what you have but there's
something there
okay then the Lama went over the
preliminary practices which you haven't
learned yet okay we will learn them next
time all right how to start your
meditation how to start
practice then the Lama went over all the
teachings he had given in the first 20
days
he went over the first four days first
four Perfections okay you are about to
undertake the last two of the six
Perfections okay these are six High
practices six High spiritual practices
for people it's called for people of
Greater scope greater scope means you
are the kind of people who want to take
what you learn in this little church out
in the budock of Mesa and go and go
change British Airways with it you know
you want to go change the whole world
you want to fix the world uh you have
this motivation okay you're not just
thinking to go home and meditate in the
corner of your house and maybe feel a
little happier okay that that will also
happen but but the goal is bigger okay
the goal is can we make a world which
has peace and actually a world which no
longer has death all right can we make a
world like that no war no hunger no
poverty no death can we make a world
like that okay that's our goal if you
have that motivation if your mind is on
that level British Airways level then
you should learn six holy practices
there are six High practices that will
have people in the world and it doesn't
again it doesn't matter that they're
Buddhist or they could have come from
anywhere it doesn't matter you can call
them lunar they came from the Moon it
doesn't matter to me I don't care at all
you see it doesn't matter the ideas are
great the ideas will help you run a 12 a
billion doll company you don't have to
know where they came from it doesn't
matter you see
uh people of highest capacity learn six
different practices you are about to
undertake the last two of those six
which are meditation and then delving
into how reality works so that you can
manipulate it to make things beautiful
things happen in your okay so these are
the last two Perfections they are found
founded on a lower teaching called the
teaching for people of medium capacity
okay and and we're going to be doing
that later all right and those are
meditations like you're going to die or
you know make your life meaningful or
things like that and then those are
founded on uh teachings for people of
least capacity least capacity people are
just worried about what's going to
happen to them when they die medium
capacity people are worried about
getting out of this whole cycle no
matter what happens to them after they
die high capacity people like you are
trying to make the world a perfect place
for for everyone okay people like you
need to study six different practices
called Perfections the last two of those
are called meditation and understanding
how the world really works okay so the
Llama went over the first four
Perfections all right
now I'm going to teach you how to study
the last two Perfections so I'm
thinking I'm going to teach you a
practice called Stillness perfect
Stillness okay in
Sanskrit sh say shamat sh perfect mental
Stillness absolute perfect you know what
did you find a lake what's under cover
your notebook did anything make it no
okay uh that's probably a l uh clear
Crystal leg your mind will become silent
still
rippl absolutely totally perfectly
silent okay
that's so then after that we'll go on to
wisdom or how to know how the world
works even on an International Airline
level you know or your health or your
relationship ship you know what are you
going to use this for I mean take it
home and use it for something right go
use it for your relationship problems
use it for your financial problems use
it for your health problems fix the war
in Ira do something with it okay got it
but you have to know how reality works
that's step two into in s
called
say if you want to mispronounce it you
can
sayana okay all right
uh uh there are six steps to learning
how to meditate now we're getting into
the nitty gritt okay there are six steps
to learning how to
meditate there are certain what do you
call it conditions you got to get ready
to meditate before you sit down to
meditate you got to get together certain
stuff certain things got to be ready
before you start to meditate even before
you start to meditate like you're going
to need a cushion you're going to have
to get your family to shut up for an
hour stuff like that okay that comes
first before you even sit down
she number
two that right
yeah then I'll give you the actual
instructions on how to meditate the real
instructions number
three based on
those instructions you are going to go
through nine different levels in your
meditation in the next few years each
one of you will climb in your meditation
through nine different beautiful levels
of of of achievement in your meditation
until your mind becomes perfectly clear
and perfectly strong now there's a cool
thing
okay
uh who is the dalama teacher and my
teacher teacher uh he said you know it
would be cool if we had a
picture of all of these meditative
levels like if there was some kind of
drawing that we could use to learn the
level it would be easier for people to
to learn it okay you want to give me a
copy can you flash it up there just a
picture I don't have it she got
it okay anyway I'm the
projector uh this is a
poster uh that was designed by TJ rupach
who wrote this whole book right wrote
down the whole book uh and and in the
Tibetan on each side it
explains the classical problems of
meditation that you will encounter for
sure and then it explains the antidotes
that you are going to use when you hit
those problems and then it explains the
cool states of mind you're going to get
into when you use those antidotes those
problems and that's the whole pictures
as you notice the elephant is black at
the bottom and there's a black monkey
which represents your distracted mind
and and then they get pure and pure
until at the very top the monk is flying
in the sky and the Elephant has a big
smile and he's all white okay and that's
the purification of your mind and then
below here we translated it uh some
years ago okay and then uh I thought it
would be cool if
I I called Kinkos we called Kinkos today
and said can you copy this and they said
yes and
uh so uh we had an idea to
uh if you want to order I I I'm going to
start teaching that tomorrow afternoon I
thought it'd be cool ifund and something
people were trying to unroll one right
next to each other
and uh so if you want one talk to who
should it be
you Angel who oh okay this is Angelo and
you can talk to him we're going to
overcharge you we're going to we're
going to add a what do you call it a
kickback on top of the charge and we're
donating that to the construction of the
cabins for the threee retreat they're in
a desperate uh stage right now
financially they got one month more to
go to build you you know couple million
dollars of cabins and they're close
they're very very close I we just did a
long review of all the progress two days
ago it took 5 hours to look at 29 Calin
we spent 5 minutes at each C it was like
unbelievable there there are 30
beautiful homemade
legal uh meditation cabin's going up and
just each Yogi is doing his or her own
cabin it's amazing and they're hardcore
and then they're going to start a three
Retreat on New Year or something like
that so we're gonna overcharge you and
we're GNA send the money there if you
want one you're welcome to order one
from
Angelo uh and if you don't want one
that's fine uh you'll still get the
whole thing okay all
right uh let's see
okay
so you will reach nine beautiful levels
of
mental peace
by by learning meditation okay and those
are reflected in the in the
poster they they thought jie D look did
I tell them how much $25 $25 I think it
cost5 or $6 to reproduce it n $9 so
we're gouging you just double okay uh
they dup means uh you will use six
powers of the mind to reach those nine
levels you don't have to worry about
that part now I w'll get to
there and then your mind will change in
four different
ways to LA and then you will get your
perfect Stillness of the mind okay don't
worry about all the numbers we'll be
doing it over the next few days okay by
the way you need the if you want the
poster at all you need it by tomorrow
okay uh because we're going to finish it
in two days Saturday and Sunday we're
going to finish it then by Tuesday we're
moving on to another subject okay all
all right here we
go is that
am you may wonder why I didn't explain
meditation and an understanding of how
things work for British Airways in the
part of the in in the 400 pages that
already came in the book I was holding
it back for now
he says I would I wanted to hold it back
until we got to the people who want to
save the world with it rather than sit
in the corner of their house with it got
it okay I've been waiting for you right
sh what is what is sham what is the
essence of
meditation how do you define the highest
and deepest form of
meditation even even people from other
Traditions okay my love used to watch
the New York Yankees he used to watch
darl Strawberry why do you think the Met
sorry it was the Mets why do you think
the Mets won the 1981 World Series you
know why did what was his name the guy
Bill Buckner dropped the ball at first
base and let the Mets win after the most
after they had got the what do you call
it the record for the worst team in
history the year before for okay my
llama was there with his
rosary and all this weird stuff happened
in the World Series especially the last
play M Wilson you know so he I saw it on
Google the other day YouTube so my llama
was going like this he says he says look
at darl strawberry's eyes right now and
the camera Zooms in on his eyes and the
PCT is coming towards him in the playoff
game last in the playoff game not the
world six and his eyes go like
this and then and then he he just swings
and the ball is a line drive to right
field and then it goes It goes like this
and then it it's supposed to come down
right and it goes and riy ch's going
like
this and it drop it hits the top of the
wall just inside the foul pole and it
drops over and they win the game
anyway why did I talk
about yeah
he say
uh anybody can learn to meditate okay
it's not a it's not a religious thing
and my llama used to say watch Geral
strawberry's eyes he's meditating he has
Sham in the moment of swinging and they
they interviewed him after the game and
they said how do you keep whacking home
runs out of the park you know he says
well today was kind of weird the ball
just but then he said um when the ball
comes to me it looks as big as a
watermelon he said I have this thing I
go into this Zone see Zone means shatan
right I go into this Zone and there's
this watermelon coming at me and I just
swing you know I hear it you know
because he has sh so what they're saying
here in the
text anybody can learn to concentrate
you know meditation is being in the zone
is anyone can do sports sports players
can do it
okay the kind of meditation that we are
seeking to develop is in fact one of the
lower ones in the world okay it's not
like the highest highest highest one all
right but we are going to Pepper that
meditation with some
seasoning called
renunciation okay we are we are tired of
living in a world where people are
hungry we are tired of living in a world
where people are fighting with each
other we are tired of living in a world
where day to day people have anxiety and
stress and and and people are dying we
are tired of that we are
sprinkling uh what's actually not the
highest level of concentration with
those thoughts of wanting to help people
and bend that boosted up to a higher
that becomes a high spiritual thing got
it if we sprinkle it with the idea that
we are seeking higher forms of shelter
okay what is a higher form of shelter
someone who can save you from death
itself okay you go for shelter nowadays
right you have a problem you call a
police right you have a legal problem
you call a
judge we call on higher truth and then
the meditation that we do is transformed
into a higher thing got it so our
meditation is differentiated
from d strawberries
concentration by this seasoning
okay and if you don't learn to meditate
with these extra
seasonings and you can study the open
teachings and you can study the secret
teachings you can study the this High
highest first and second levels of
secret teachings
but you will never get it okay you will
never grasp it you know that you'll
understand the words but it will not
happen to you you know like in the
higher teachings there are teachings on
how to meet Angels okay you go to the
what do you call it
Safeway you go to Safeway and you meet
an angel and Angel you meet an angel in
aisle
three you say today I'm going to meet an
angel in aisle 3 of Safeway you know
like I don't need a burning bush or
anything you'll just be a free
safely and and then you just go and
they're there okay you can predict it
you can make it happen Okay but if you
can't meditate it's not going to happen
right you can you can someone can sit
here up here and tell you oh you know
there's this practice you can make
Angels appear in Isle 3 at Safeway at
4:00 if you can get there on time you
know and and then you say yeah how teach
me how to do that and then I'm going to
say if you can't meditate I can't teach
you if you don't have that level
Stillness of a of a silent Lake
Stillness of the surface of a silent
Lake if you can't reach that level you
can't do the Safeway thing okay so if
you don't want to do the Safeway thing
okay don't learn to meditate I don't
care
okay you want to know sh is it's like
you go to the edge of the river and you
want to bring back a bucket of water for
your house which is half a mile away
from the river you better have a bucket
okay what's he
say you want to bring those ideas back
to your mind you need shamat you need to
medicate you need that perfect still Leg
State of Mind to get the water okay or
it's not going to happen all those
realizations will never you will never
have a safer experience and they're fun
they are really fun okay they are really
fun
okay that's what sh is you want
know you have to learn to meditate so
strongly perfectly perfectly stable you
could have your eyes closed someone
could wave McDonald's french fries in
front of your nose and you wouldn't
smell a effect got it okay that's what
it says right here and then
uh
de if you want to see the world save
from war hunger
suffering if all you want to do is save
yourself don't get good you must reach
the direct perception of emptiness you
have to see emptiness if you want to
save the world or if all you want to do
is save yourself you have to
see to get to that you need sh you need
perfect meditation you cannot see
emptiness directly without perfect
meditation it's never going to happen
Okay so we are we are learning how to
see this directly we are learning this
the platform or the State of Mind from
which you will see corly I'm going to
give you a break in about 10 minutes
okay I'm trying to get as much mileage
out of you before you car out
[Music]
okay before you can see the real nature
of reality so you can go teach the
British
Airways you need need a stable and
perfectly silent State of Mind you must
have a perfectly silent state of mind
and then he gives an
examp if you're in a Tibetan cave and in
tiet the meditators over hundreds of
years they have been
drawing beautiful paintings on the sides
of the cave because they're too bored to
meditate and and uh it's called de de
means mural cave murals so they've been
painting these beautiful murals on the
sides of the caves but the problem is
you go to the cave and you can't see
them because it's a cave and it's dark
so he says if you want to see those
murals you have to take a a lamp you
know in tobet it would be a butter lamp
right you would have you would carry a
butter lamp in but if there's a wind
right what do you call it draft if it's
drafty then the the butter lamp shakes
and you can't see the the picture
beautifully
okay you need a state of mind you need a
state of meditation which is absolutely
perfectly still and only with that then
can your the light of your mind see
Ultimate Reality you cannot get to the
guts of reality if you don't have the
capacity to bring your mind to Total
Stillness it won't happen any more than
you could see a mural on the side of a
dark cave if the wind was blowing to the
cave got it if if the mind is unstable
you won't be able to get what I'm saying
when I went to British Airways when we
all went to British Airways we had to
meditate with them in the morning
because that was the only way they could
get it in the afternoon got it okay
moreover if you learn to meditate well
then as you go through the rest of this
book over the next 10 years you will get
it you will be able to meditate on each
one of those steps and you will rise
through the steps to Enlightenment you
will walk up a steady Stairway to
Enlightenment if you can meditate and if
you can't you won't got it I'm telling
you this is the first night of 10 years
you see this is the first night of 10
years work and these are the first
sentences of 10 years of Blaha you know
and I'm telling you now don't come back
to me in 5 years and say you know back
in 2010 you told us to meditate and I
didn't do it you know don't be one of
those sms okay it comes to me in 5 years
and say yeah you know back in 2010 like
the very first night you said we had to
learn to meditate but I didn't have time
or something don't drive me crazy okay
this is this is the time we're starting
fresh a lot of you have had some
training before or a lot of training
before now let's start fresh I'm saying
from the first night you won't get
anywhere unless you have a daily
meditation practice and a good one and
and you're going to get the right
instructions you know you can get yoga
awesomeness anywhere for example good
teachers of yoga awesomeness are all
over the place it's very exciting I can
I went to flag Stu the other day with
some friends and we had a great class
you know in a small class in a small
town there were like 15 people doing
handstands you know I was like wow you
can get yoga anywhere you can't get
meditation anywhere nowhere you know
they sit down and say empty your mind
you know or something
anyway you're going to get the real
thing and you're going to get you know
the real poop then you can use it you
know it'll be nice but you got to do it
and then the rest of the 10 years will
be he says K means it'll be a cinch
everything will be easy after that but
starting tonight you got to make a
commitment to learn to meditate because
that without that we won't get anywhere
okay five more minutes okay I'll give
you a break I promise but
I'm you know he says there are books
even by Lord the lamp of the
P where he says Hey look you could learn
to fly if you could learn to meditate
you could learn to fly or you could see
the future you could see next year's
lottery
numbers you could see the steps the
British year had to take to get out of
their financial crisis ahead of time and
then just show it you see you could do
weird stuff but he says but they send
something that's not the important
stuff good only the main reason you and
I want to learn to meditate
[Music]
she sh he called sh
who he
said you're going to
use the pasana you're going to use your
knowledge of how the world really works
to destroy your own negative emotions
okay you're going to use your
understanding of how reality works not
for financial gain but to destroy your
own negative
emotions so I advise you to start with
meditation start your practice by
learning how to meditate because you
will use your meditation to see the
nature reality and with that you will
you will destroy the negativities in
your mind your mind will become pure and
happy your mind will become totally pure
and happy okay but you got to learn to
meditate
first so we must start with perfect
[Music]
meditation there's another attitude and
then we'll stop okay there's another
attitude
called uh bu
right it's a love for the whole world a
love for every person in the world
there's a there's a high spiritual
attainment called B love for every
person living creature in the world and
not just this world but many many worlds
okay countless worlds there's a high
spiritual attainment called true love
for all living creatures and he
says you can pick that up before you
learn to meditate or after you learn to
meditate doesn't matter okay
so you have to start meditating now
whether you get good at that first or
whether you develop ultimate love first
we can't say and there's no it's not
necessary to worry about it okay maybe
you will hit the peaks of meditation
first maybe you will hit the peak of
compassion first don't worry about it
either way it'll be okay that's what he
says she can
talk okay so I think uh now that half
the people are
asleep uh we should take a break is that
a is that a Sarah thing it is yeah Sarah
food fun okay so anyway we're selling no
is
it okay so every year we send a group of
young people to my Monastery uh Tibetan
monaster and uh we pay for their trip
and we pay for their airfare and then
they spend there and my hope is that uh
couple of them will be sitting up here
in 20
years uh I turned a plan ahead so really
so uh we have these little dumb big
sales and we overcharge you for uh very
bad food and then uh just the money all
goes to their aort okay so try to eat a
lot and uh overpay as much as you can
and uh we always it's going very well
how many years now five years I think
six years now they've been going and
it's been very beautiful so we'll be
doing that I think
yeah so for for the posters that that um
people are going to um order from Angelo
we're we're ordering them tonight and
we're getting them pressed tonight so
you if you want one you must tell Angelo
tonight and he'll take your name down
and then we'll bring them tomorrow and
give you them tomorrow but we're only
going to print exactly as many as people
ask us for so please uh tell Angelo and
he'll write your name and that'll be a
an order and then you can pay for the
poster
tomorrow Angelo will be standing
somewhere around the stage waving a
notebook all right have a nice bre oh if
you want to come and uh talk for a
moment uh please feel free I'll stay
here and then um try to be considered of
other people who might want to you know
maybe they have a serious medical
problem or something just imagine that
the person behind you in line has a very
serious problem they have to talk about
and and then if if we can't talk tonight
I'm happy to talk we're I'm here for 10
days and and we can talk anytime so just
make a line and then we can talk a okay
please have a nice we'll come back in 10
minutes
okay okay we'll start
it means
uh whether you are
uh whether you are seeking goals for
yourself whether you are seeking goals
for others
or whether you are practicing the secret
teachings to help others in a single
lifetime if you learn to meditate with
complete Stillness then you can achieve
all these
goals what do you call in great bounds
okay it means jumping across
the but if you want to learn to meditate
deeply you have to start out with the
proper condition to meditate deeply and
if you don't you will never get good at
[Music]
it uh the lamp on the path
by
says if you can't get together the
proper conditions for learning to
meditate or for your meditation practice
you can make efforts for a long
time you can try to meditate for a
thousand years if you don't get the
proper conditions ready ahead of time
you can try to meditate for a thousand
years but you will never achieve perfect
concentration it's not going to happen
so what are the conditions that you need
before you sit down on your pillow okay
what on your meditation seat what are
what are the conditions you have to what
do you call Inc it's it's
uh uh
assemble like gather all the right
conditions even before you sit down on
your cushion
[Music]
okay so we're going to cover six
different things six different
conditions that that you have to get
together if you're going to get serious
about your meditation even before you
meditate okay six things you have to
assemble or gather or I don't
know conditions that you have to put
together something
okay you will need a place to meditate
which is conducive for meditation number
one number
two you have to reduce
your needs okay CH you have to learn to
be happy with what you have
already uh you have to start giving up
excess stimulation excess activity
okay this is very
interesting you must become a more
highly ethical person you have to watch
your ethics if you hope to meditate well
you can't cheat on your taxes even
slightly you can't lie to your brothers
and sisters even slightly you know you
can't mess around with someone else's
partner even slightly and expect a
meditate it's not going to happen that's
one of the preconditions how's that
preconditions uh you should try to clean
your mind of all those random thoughts
like I want ice cream okay like that
dumble KN okay so he's going to cover
those six in detail ready what was the
first
one what you call place right
do the place where you hope to meditate
should have five qualities all right so
this is a typical galupa list there's
going to be six preconditions that you
have to get ready before you Med
meditate and the first one has five
parts got it the place where the
conducive place where you're going to be
meditating is going to have five
different
qualities he's quoting the alar which
was written
by written down by a taking dictation
from my the next Buddha to come in this
world very close now within 500 years or
maybe not that long
so he gives a verse spoken by the coming
Buddha to describe the five qualities
that the place where you're going to
meditate should have you should look for
a place to meditate that has these five
qualities I'm just going to mention the
names of them and then we'll go into
what they are okay and this is from a
verse stuff should be easy to find
number one stuff should be easy to find
what stuff he's talking about is coming
okay
uh it should be a perfect place what
that means is coming s it should be a
perfect location how does that different
from a perfect place we'll we'll talk
about it talk
you should have perfect
companions when you
meditate how many is
that uh oh
oh and you should have all the required
articles for what what that means we'll
find out
[Music]
okay so now he's on to the first one
which
was Stu you're going to easy to find
okay stuff need is easy to find like Rob
ringer has your threeyear retreat prop
pain needs cover
okay if you are trying to undertake some
deep Retreat or you're trying to let's
say we're going to Prescott for 10 days
right we're going to reserve 10 days for
learning to meditate okay if during that
time we we can't have the what called
the basic necessities of life that you
need like food uh heating it's going to
be called okay uh you know place to
sleep stuff like that if you don't have
these basic necessities of life they
cheer drone to good on your you're going
to have to get in the car and go to
Prescott and buy stuff okay so you don't
want to do that you want to be your
place should be well stocked ahead of
time or you should have an RTV all ring
okay
uh the food and other materials that you
use for your practice should be pure
they should not be Ted by uh bad Deeds
okay for example
uh the killing of an animal okay if you
want to learn to meditate
well and you're just trying to decide
what to eat uh while you're while you're
trying to learn to meditate if you put
into your body a substance which was
derived from the murder of a of an
innocent creature like a
dumb Pleasant cow who never hurt anybody
and and didn't know what was coming you
know innocently being friended you and
and lived in your pasture and ate your
food and then you came out one day with
a you know and slid his throat you know
then if you eat that kind of thing and
you put it in your body and then you try
to meditate it's not going to happen all
right so the the Articles and the food
that you use while you're trying to
learn to meditate should be gotten
cleanly and honestly okay and without
harming other creatures okay you can't
like steal things you can't
you can't be living in a house which is
some problem you're not paying rent or
the person's you know something like
that cheating somebody or something like
that these are all the stuff around you
when you want to become a meditation
master has to be clean okay almonds are
really good almond milk is really good
fresh oranges are really good fresh
vegetables are really good okay minimum
harm to other beings all right okay
all the have said
that when we say stuff is easy to
find good what we mean easy to find
is easy to find in a clean way without
hurting other people without hurting
other people okay so when they say easy
to find it doesn't mean that there's a
mall next to your retreat C it means
the people taking care of your through
your retreat are careful to select foods
and and objects which have been gotten
honestly and and without harm to other
beings okay they've been acquired uh
through honest means the accounting is
good for the money that was donated
everything is clean and pure and then
your meditation will go well
[Music]
okay as regards to the actual place
where you meditate
[Music]
you should try to find like a meditation
cabin or or a spot where some holy
person has meditated before okay like
try to find uh like we don't have in
this country many places because we
don't have a custom of meditation yet
but in so far as you can try to find a
place which has been blessed by the
presence of a great meditator before
Okay then if you go and sit I slept on
R's bed for 25 years you know I had
incredible dreams and stuff you know he
when when I got there he gave me his bed
that he had been using and and it was
extraordinary every night was a trip uh
so uh you know try to or use a cushion
that some holy being has sat on or you
know try to get something that has a
blessing
[Music]
okay for beginners or for people who are
just starting out on their journey in
the practice of meditation it's
important that the blessing Comes This
Way got it what's the
implication when you get good at
meditation you'll be doing the blessing
you'll bless somebody's house you know
somebody invit you to Thanksgiving
dinner which we're going to do shortly
and then uh you come to the house and
you bless the house because you're a
good meditator got it but at the
beginning you're trying to get the
process to come this way we're trying to
find stuff and places that have been
blessed by more experienced meditators
okay later the implication is that later
you're going to walk into somebody's
house and bless it just by The Vibes of
your good meditation okay
if if in your particular country there's
not a lot of there hasn't been a
thousand years of
meditators uh at least don't meditate in
a place that has a negative energy avoid
places that have a negative energy and
he gives the example of uh a place where
someone is living who has broken their
commitments and vows okay
uh for example I mean inarm it says uh
someone who has taken a a military vow
to harm other beings someone who has
stood and sworn that they will harm
other
beings uh and made a promise then
there's a negative energy about them and
and you wouldn't want to do your
meditation in
a in a house like that something like
that okay like if there's a negative
energy where people have been hurting
other people then you would want to
avoid that kind of a influence vibes
right
okay didn't there are places where there
has been great conflict we have a place
like that at D mountain right uh at our
University there is an area where uh the
native people were killed and gono was
captured there and and there has been a
kind of a negative energy there which I
think has been cleansed now but you
as a beginner you shouldn't just pop
down on a place where lots of native
people have been slaughtered and expect
to have a good meditation okay don't go
to a place of bad
[Music]
vies watch out for places that have a
lot of lions and tigers and
bears
uh Chun means uh Bandits but we don't
have that we're lucky in America you
know you're really lucky in America I
mean most countries
most meditators have had to worry they
go out in the wilderness and they're
worried someone will just show up with a
gun and shoot them and take all their
food you know what I mean we're lucky to
live in this country
okay watch out for places that have
negative Spirits like haunted places or
like
that you need a place which already has
a nice blessing
if you stay in a place which has a
negative energy and which even may have
a spirit beings negative Spirit
beings and you just kind of innocently
say I'm going to do it here
anyway without any real appreciation of
the dangers of that kind of place
CH you will come you will have problems
you will have problems you know you you
could approach a negative place with a
kind of an innocence but but it can come
back to hunt you you know don't don't
try to take on all the spirit beings in
Mesa Arizona okay find a place that find
a place in Mesa which is which is pure
[Music]
okay then the Lama told a story about a
good practitioner of Lama who had
ignored warnings not to do do their
meditation in a negative in a place of
negative energy and then later they had
a real problem some kind of Spirit came
and harmed them
okay himself was harmed by spirits and
and he had Wars with Spirits later in
his life according to tradition uh you
can see the effects on his body if you
see a photo of him later he was all
blown up and he had had
major struggles with spirit and he had
prevailed but it had ruined his body
right so it's
important how do you get rid of negative
forces or negative Spirits if you sense
them in the place where you're
meditate he says contrary to what you
might think you should try to be
friendly and you should try to have
compassion for them and you should try
to be gentle with
them try to get to know them leave out
little offerings for them talk to them
kindly and try to people do this with
roaches right it works
okay try to get the spirit to be on your
side okay by being gentle and thoughtful
and talk to them and try to become
friends okay rather than trying to like
harm
it now we came to S which was a we said
good location as a to a good place and
we said what's the difference between a
perfect location and a perfect place
right say yes okay that way I know
you're way
okay good location
means it shouldn't be too hot and it
shouldn't be too
cold D about this B right uh okay but
anyway generally you should try to find
a place where it's rather temperate uh
the temperature it fits your body and
fits your personality and if it doesn't
you should take some steps to make it
that way okay as far as you can uh don't
don't suffer don't try to try to make
your retreat Place comfortable okay
temperature- wise and then uh especially
if it's so cold or so hot that it might
cause uh illness or or some kind of
imbalance in your body okay
the place the the soil of the place and
the water of the place should be healthy
okay like I live in a place where the
water has been tainted with
Arsenic and we have to be very careful
we have to clean it carefully and and so
uh make sure that the environment around
you has been taken care of nicely you
know that people are respecting the
environment and they're not harming the
environment like with chemicals or
things like
[Music]
that as for your companions okay people
that you choose to meditate
with uh they should be people that you
get along with and people who are
interested in the same sort of
activities that you are you know like if
you are interested in doing a a
meditation on the on sh after having
trained yourself in the details of it
well then you should try to meditate
with people who are who have had a
similar training and who have similar
what do you
call aspirations okay try to meditate
with people who have similar aspirations
that you
[Music]
have there's an expression in toet it
says
uh meditate with a second shadow just
meditate with
a meditate with a sh a
shadow meditate with a shadow as your
friend it's an old toet expression
meditate with a shadow as your friend
and and then he says some people
misunderstood the meaning of it meditate
with a shadow as your friend and and I
looked it up you know because of the
kindness of uh many many people over the
last what 22 years we have in the
computer we have I don't know a million
pages of scriptures Tibetan scriptures
have been input so I can look up
something like this and I found out who
spoke it it was spoken by the
fif okay he he said he said meditate
with a shadow as your friend and then
you know
what 400 years later no 300 years
later is is is quoting here and he says
people misunderstood what the
because they thought he was
saying meditate always meditate by
yourself right with your sh if nobody's
in the room but your Shadow you're by
yourself right so people have
misunderstood the quotation by the
fifth says that's not what the fifth
meant he
says it doesn't
mean it doesn't mean you have to
meditate by yourself and there shouldn't
be anybody else in
rather it means and I looked up some
other scriptures
uh it means when you get up what does
your Shadow
do when you go to the refrigerator to
get uh some
pie what does your Shadow do it goes to
referat to get some pie got it when you
want to do yoga you know you want to do
a headstand what does your Shadow do
head it does a headstand okay so he's
saying it means you should find
meditation companions who are as
likeminded as you as your Shadow you
know when you want to meditate for an
hour they're like good you know when you
want to meditate extra in the evening
they're like great you know they are
following you as much as your Shadow got
it
okay uh
let he is he's very adant here and it's
unusual I think he says people who are
beginning a practice of meditation
should not do it alone he says
uh he says it would be a problem it
would be a serious problem people who
are learning to meditate should not try
to meditate alone
[Music]
okay he says I think groups of at least
three meditators is good uh
at at least
three drop M leg if you can find a group
of people who have similar spiritual
aspirations then the more you could get
together for your retreat it would be
good you know if you were doing retreat
in a group or if you were doing like in
January we're going to do ret treat if
you can get a whole room full of people
who have the same aspirations and if you
meditate together it's much more
powerful okay uh my first lava
ging uh he uh when he got to this point
he took a pencil he grabbed the pencil
and he broke it and he said that's one
person meditating and then he grabbed
the 10 pencils and he
went and he said you know look how much
stronger 10 are you know so like if you
can find people that you are really
tight with then it's good to meditate
with other people okay I do that almost
every day I I try to meditate other
people it's it's good it doesn't mean
that it's not useful to have long
periods where you do meditate alone you
can also make great progress alone but
in a in a beginner if you have the
support of other people you're I guess
you're more likely to do the
meditation all right
[Music]
uh mix
this was a I almost said a but I
won't say that uh this was really hard
and I looked through thousands of pages
you know and uh I found it but it's very
rare extremely rare he
says
uh no matter how many meditation
companions you choose to
have uh they should be people that when
you look out of the corner of your eye
they are
heavy and then what it means is they
should be hardcore if you if you choose
someone to be your even with yoga right
like if you choose to do your yoga with
other people it's good to do it with
hardcore people I I used to play tennis
in high school which is not hardcore uh
but our coach during the season he had a
rule we were not allowed to play with
anyone who was not better than us you
see we were we were never allowed during
season to play a tennis match with
someone who wasn't better than us you
see and uh and in meditation it's the
same okay in choosing your meditation
buddies look for hardcore look for
heavyweight he says look for heavyweight
you know how you going to a restaurant
and you like sense this presence over
here and you're like you're like you're
afraid to look at like a biker you know
that's what he's talking about that's
someone that you would just look out of
the corner of your eye and they look
heavy and you you're afraid to
like you know like what kind of beer are
you having you know like
uh okay hardcore pick a hardcore person
he
[Music]
says don't hang out with
lightweight okay he says uh b b mea
means
just sort of flitty people you know what
I mean who are not very serious about
the practice don't hang out with that
kind of people cuz it'll rub off hang
out with people who meditate better than
you hang out with yoga teachers who are
better than you and they'll push you
right okay something uh this is a
beautiful line it's all beautiful we
should do the whole thing tonight uh
this is we were talking about the other
day
[Music]
say the thorn of meditation is
noises okay the thorn of meditation is
noise the one thing that can destroy
your meditation
is sounds like random sounds
uh try doing a retreat with one of those
battery clocks that clicks T you know
you're like deep in it's going thick
thick diick thick you know
or I don't know with a mouse in the room
you know that's really bad like you're
meditating and
then refrigerators are really bad like
you're going to spoil a lot of food if
he gets serious about
meditation cuz you'll unplug the fridge
before you start and you'll forget to
plug it back in and then suddenly you
have a in your living room from the I
not it okay it should be like that okay
I mean stop all the noises in
your you got to stop you got to deal
with noise you got to I uh have friends
who just uh use they carry around
earplugs like you can buy packs now like
20 earplugs for
$3 and and just carry them around like
that that's very good it's very useful
okay try to find a place that is quiet
sh
during the day you get people bling
during the night you get dogs
[Music]
barking oh Chu means
uh the the noise of of a stream nearby
or something like that okay although I
found the of kind help
anyway my mama used to say
you should take this the subject that
you're going to meditate about and you
should analyze it
carefully but also you have to get all
your stuff ready so he's on to
number all right okay here's what my
llama said about getting your stuff
ready who llama
you got to get your stff together what
is before you start your threee retreat
or before you start a serious meditation
session you should have gotten the
proper empowerments you should have
gotten the proper teachings you should
have in your hand all the thought and
all the books that you're going to need
okay everything should be that's what it
means okay all your stuff all the stuff
should be very good
deep say
uh
say okay this is a famous K story when
he got at this point see you have this
benefit of
uh of of all of Kim R's stories he
probably heard from CH which he probably
heard from which is cool right so you're
getting all the inside
info so there was a guy uh in Tibet who
went to fight with an Invader to his
country and uh you know the Tibetans are
not they had flit
lck with with Yak horns
you know and you know you load the thing
and you put some Gunpowder in and you
put in a what do you call a ball a metal
ball and then you pull back the flint
lock and then you go and then goof and
then and then the ball goes you know and
they weren't very good at fighting so
anyway so just rag tag people go to
protect the country they go with guns
and and they're Mar they know they just
go from their farm and they walk towards
the front line
and then the guy uh had to go to the
bathroom and he saw an ous so he went
into an ous and he he pooped but he left
his gun there and then he went to the
front he reached the front lines and and
here comes this massive hord of enemy
soldiers you know and he's like and he
looks for his gun you know and he's
like he left his gut then he pooped out
of
fear he pooped right and then was like
just a minute I'm I'll just go back and
get my gun you know at the I left it at
the ous you know it means uh so in
tibetan they
say he
shot he shot where he was supposed to
poop but then he pooped where he was
supposed to
shoot something like
that anyway it means get everything
ready
[Music]
time the main point is he says very
beautiful the main stuff that you have
to get ready for your meditation is
training okay you have to be trained in
meditation and you have to know what
you're going to practice before you
close your door for this threee Retreat
you better have six or seven years of
training and texts ready right and and
you you you know what you're supposed to
do when you close the door got it
[Music]
okay nowadays he's complaining what is
nowadays 1921 in Tibet right he says
people are all freaked out about their
cab and their propane and their and
their refrigerator and all the other
stuff and they don't even know what
they're going to do when they Clos the
door they don't have any plan for what
door they don't have any practices ready
they don't have any training they're
just all worried about am I going to
have my yak meat ready and you know
they're not thinking about well wouldn't
be Yak meat right
okay he says this is a what do you call
it in colloquial English
pitiful this is
lame means this is lame these people are
lame okay like they're all they're all
worried about their cabin and they're
not thinking about what they're going to
do when they get in cabin but you guys
have both right
okay some of them are so bad that just
before they go into the cabin to do
their three retreat they go to the llama
and say could you do a mole for me about
what I should practice in the retreat
like they didn't decide until the last
day to ask the Llama to just sort of
guess that what they might like to do
okay there are people like that you see
now
this you got to get your practices ready
before you shut yourself away okay
that's why we're doing this class before
we go to Prescot okay cuz then when you
get the Prescott you'll have everything
in your head then we're going to sit
down and shut up and meditate right
which you'll
probably probably don't believe I can do
that but we're going to try Okay uh I
want to make sure I don't go too
far
okay I'm not stopping till we finish the
material okay if that's if you don't
like that you just don't come back okay
all right or you can leave uh I'm just
cuz we have to do two and a half pages a
day for the next 10 years or it's going
to be 20 years I don't know if we can
make it okay but it's not going to be
late don't
[Music]
worry so he finished the discussion
about the conducive meditation what's
number
[Music]
two what
perfect no reduce your need yeah reduce
your needs okay reduce your
needs ruce your the needs that you have
in your
okay don't be so worried about having a
lot of food or very good food don't be
so worried about having nice clothes or
you know a lot of
clothes uh
that's all he just says reduce your
needs to a
minimum the more stuff you have the more
maintenance you have to do the more
meditation sessions you will miss the
more meditation sessions you miss the
closer you are to just dying a
meaningless like a meaningless life okay
you have to set up your you need a nice
place to live you need a comfortable
place to live you need a place where the
water's not dripping on your head and
the mice are not running around on you
cuz you can't meditate you know you need
a decent quiet modest
clean quiet home uh you need a place to
meditate but then stop there because if
you every every extra object you
accumulate you have to take care of it
and and then that waste time and it
fills up your mind okay all right s CH
cha means number three means uh be happy
with what you get okay be grateful and
happy with what you
get if all you get is some you
know what lousy food you know like
whatever food you can get in Retreat
they're going to deliver something
there's a thing for monkss in the
monastery very strong tradition eat what
you're given and be grateful and don't
wh about it you know think God has given
me this food or whoever you know and
it's not what I wanted but I'm grateful
you know I'm grateful for the people who
who work to make the food I'm grateful
the people who cooked it I'm grateful to
the people who brought it here people
lost many hours of their precious
Irreplaceable lifetime to deliver that
food to your plate be grateful for God's
sake and stop worrying that it's under
or it's overcooked or it's too greasy or
it's not exactly what you wanted don't
look at food that way look at food like
oh look a gift from thousands of people
in in the in the chain of of what do you
call the market right thousands of
people have worked like they've lost
their lives to bring me this plate of
food then be thankful and don't look at
it like oh I don't like that or that has
too much salt or you know that isn't
what I wanted you know like that okay it
just makes your life happy be grateful
with what you get and be turned on by
what you get and think about wow you
know hundreds of people were to make
this for me to get this food to me it's
not just the people who delivered it on
the what do you call RTV thing what's
RTV rough terrain vehicle something is
it you nobody
knows but anyway it's not just the
people who delivered it to the door it's
hundreds of people in the in the in the
production chain and be grateful to them
they they sacrifice their time in their
life and don't sit there and whine about
oh it's got too much greef or I don't
like it's too cold or you know don't
look at food like that look at it like a
miracle cuz it is uh and a Sacrifice by
other people
[Music]
right and the same with your
clothing if you're not a person who can
reduce their needs and if you're not a
person who can be grateful with what
they get do
if you just try to collect more stuff
for your
house if you just try to collect
different kinds of food for your
refrigerator and and you get into the
process of it's called in it's called so
say so so means collection and
protection first you get the food then
you have to I mean my refrigerator is
like now I have a refrigerator I never
had a refrigerator and now I'm in the so
wa so soon right I have to check which
vegetables are getting old and I have to
eat those first you know and then my
mind is all like oh the zucchini are is
the zucchini older or the carrots are
older you know and then you
know just lower the amount of stuff in
the fridge okay uh because otherwise
means you will be distracted in you will
not be able to get to deep states of
meditation if you are worrying about are
the carrots older or are the Z Kies
older
okay what's our next
one yeah you should be living a highly
ethical life otherwise you won't be able
to men
it hey he's got it out of order it's not
my
phone it's coming it's coming I think he
wanted to talk about s daa first
generally
speaking being an ethical person is the
foundation for all spiritual success
okay generally speaking being a nice
person is the is the basis of all
spiritual
success removing your subtle
inner distraction
relies upon removing your growth outer
distraction
[Music]
okay if you are pled by your
conscience okay then your mind won't
be centered
okay so try to get some self
control over the things you say and the
things you do and the things you think
okay try to reach some level of
self-control about the degree to which
you harm other beings okay and
dck your mind will become peaceful make
your mind
peaceful by being very careful not to
hurt other people and other creatures
okay then your meditation will be good
now if you fail to give up over
stimulation he's he's coming to that one
okay he's on that one duni is a very
nice word those of you who care where'
it go is it up
there it's the very first word there
okay D say d d he's doing a good job
okay you should think uh d means uh Dy
means busyness with a
Y busy with the wife is tsy like you I
got so stuff to do that's
useless things that you've made for
yourself to do oh he made a list here it
says
email yeah
email and surfing the
web if you waste your time just fling
with other people about
stuff that's called chat rooms right
chatting
[Music]
texting you have
to look upon email and texting and
chatting and surfing in the context of
something that could prevent you from
succeeding in your meditation
forever okay like you have to bravely
cons consider the importance of what
you're doing with your email and the
other stuff you know don't send fluff to
other people I have I have what do you
call it a spam filter on my Google
account but I have a Fluff filter in my
head you know and if I just see who it's
from and I don't even open it you know
it's like this person sends me fluff you
know they send me something their
grandmother
said
just don't send anything that is not
important okay or meaningful or or even
loving you see meaningful in a loving
way something that has content don't
send stuff that doesn't have content
okay keep your activities F keep your
needs few good in order to protect your
meditation he says not just for you know
good luck or something to protect your
meditation watch how much you take on
and watch how much busy stuff you do to
protect your meditation see it as a way
of protecting your
meditation if you stick to the principle
of not wanting too much stuff and if you
stick to the principle of being deeply
grateful for whatever comes to you
automatically your activities will be
less you see automatically your level of
business busyness will decrease if you
don't need a lot of stuff and if you
have this heartfelt gratitude for
whatever comes to you you will find that
automatically you need L and you want
got it
[Music]
okay there were other uh
secondary spiritual practices spiritual
Arts what you you could call what minor
spiritual
Arts uh one of them was
uh Cari means uh like Bic astrology okay
uh
like telling people's future with from
the stars and stuff like that which
which has a deep uh philosophical
foundation in Tibet okay but it's
considered a secondary spiritual thing
it's not like meditating or trying to
develop compassion okay
men means the practice of medicine which
was a secondary what do you call
application for many monks many monks
were uh healers okay Mo death means what
do you call it doing
uh divinations for people with dice you
know people come and ask me what nation
I get married on and
you
okay uh Tron trono means uh people say
in Tibet there grew a custom where uh
and I was a victim of this uh the monks
somebody would call the monastery and
say I want 18 months at my house to to
recite the diamond cter Sutra from 400
p.m. to 8:00 p.m. and then I'll promise
I'll give them a turkey dinner or
something you know and this is some kind
of custom into bed and I had to do it
for years for 20 years and um that's
called Tong choke Tong choke means Town
rituals you have to walk to town and
read Diamond sura to people who are half
asleep and it's like Latin to them they
have no idea what you're saying and then
you get a turkey dinner
okay he says give up these things also
give up the
minor spiritual things that are not
really important okay because they are
also busy nurs
[Music]
minor slightly spiritual
engagements and activities are not only
dangerous for us beginners he says but k
d YY even those High llamas High
spiritual practitioners they they are
also endangered by this kind of thing
they also have to be careful they can
also be tempted by these minor spiritual
things he an
example who is
that okay remember lived 1290 1364 you
know him he was an influence on Jessa
uh Jessa was too young to meet him but
he was strongly influenced by he
assembled the
con the the the Canon of of Buddhist
practice U 4 and half th000
Tex and lad damba lad damba means
uh holy Lama okay but it's a particular
person named uh sunam Johnson who lived
1312 to 1375 and he's a important Sak
Lama anyway these are two important
major llamas of their time okay of the
1300s
there was a
spirit you're going to get a lot of this
stuff okay I don't know if you believe
it or not but anyway there's a spirit
being called bear in tiet the name comes
from bear which is a Corruption of bhara
okay so bear comes from bhara and this
was a a spirit being who lived in he
wanted to ruin these two high llamas
practice he went after these llamas were
getting too good at meditation they call
ined they call uh what do you call it
their head came up over the what do you
call it in the radar in English you say
uh they came onto the spirit's
radar bad spirits oh these guys are
learning to medit let's get them what do
you call keep your head
down they they like they say if you get
if you start getting serious about your
practice you will attract trouble they
don't like it there are there are Spirit
beings who don't like it okay so the
minute you start getting serious about
your meditation they start doing a
construction project next door with a
tractor those guys they look like these
fat construction guys but they're not
they are they are Spirit beings probably
pay hard okay uh so the minute you start
doing something right they will come
really they will come in all sorts of
forms right they don't want you to
meditate okay so anyway he wanted to
ruin these two high L meditation so CH
Pua he gave them an iron pen in totic
was a big deal to have an iron pen
because you use bamboo stick the word
for pen is Nuku which means bamboo and
you know 99% of the population used a
bamboo stick and they dipped it in ink
and they they they wrote things right
but if you really big person you got an
iron pen okay so he offered them an iron
pen the demon offered the two high Lamas
and IR
each and he taught them how to do
complicated astrological charts and they
each ched up a thousand metal pens in
their life doing complicated
astrological projections got it
CH and they didn't get to their
spiritual goals you nowadays it would be
something like
Facebook okay unless you were using it
for Spiritual purposes okay but really I
mean nowadays the de parar would offer
you a Facebook account okay something to
kind of waste your time pleasantly and
then suddenly you're old and it's too
late to meditate okay it happens i' I've
met I've met people recently I met a guy
I think it was in Pennsylvania he says
you don't remember me you I came to Har
New Jersey the same year you did and I
was in Kev P's kitchen the same day you
were when you started and look where you
got to and I wasted my whole life I
wasted the last 40 years you know and I
was in the kitchen with you on the first
day and I should have stay you know I
wasted my tongue I blew it he I blew it
you know and then so don't let Facebook
I mean now okay don't let beart come and
Facebook you
okay I'm not kidding right I'm not
kidding and it should be something
rather challenging and interesting and
you right I mean a good Demon won't come
to you with the world what do you call
Super Bowl on TV you know he'll come to
you with something kind of deeper and
and interesting and
sophisticated so you you can waste your
life like feeling you're doing something
when you're not okay got it like doing
astrological
calculations his name was
the he lived in the same era as those
other llamas 1295
1369 he wrote a wonderful commentary on
uh master sh's
workat and we studied it the first
classes I ever had we studied it it's
very beautiful
um told me S he was meditating on
compassion okay and
love he's rather than
learning uh
programming uh he sat in the corner and
meditated on love and
compassion they and the demon never
touched him the demon couldn't get to
him the demon tried and he couldn't get
to him he tried to tempt him with you
know like power and knowledge and fame
and all he wanted to do was sit and
meditate about people love for other
people and the demon couldn't he
wouldn't take the iron pen got it he
refused the Facebook account and he and
he sat in the corner and he meditated on
the suffering of the world and the demon
couldn't touch him got it
[Music]
himself wrote 18 volumes of scripture to
10,000 pages
okay and it was a custom
INB that when you wrote a a heavy
scripture at the front you would put the
the title of the book in three different
languages okay uh Tibet and then in two
forms of Sanskrit called and something
else L and L these are very ornate they
take a lot of years to learn I learned
some of them they take a long time to
learn you have to use a special
calligraphy pen and it was a sign that
you were a great scholar right that you
could write the title of your book in
three languages okay Jess Kaa never did
that okay why
it's not that he didn't know Sanskrit
verti means uh deor means SII the comp
proper composition of Sanskrit sys and
jati means the
proper Sanskrit poetical meter which is
very these things are very difficult to
learn the rules of composition and the
rules of poetic metering it's not that J
Anda didn't know
them rather he was afraid that getting
sidetracked by minor knowledges would
ruin his practice okay he was worried
about getting sidetracked to minor
subjects that would ruin his his higher
practice okay M so he didn't he didn't
do those things
okay I myself who's
I I myself was trying to do is very
difficult s means a complicated
astrological chart okay considering many
planets movements at the same time okay
now there's
computers they if you go on the internet
you can find a they do it by computer
but in the old days it took a long
time I spent one year doing one
astrological calculation one chart one
good complicated chart of says I took a
year on
[Music]
one CH I wore a hole in my finger on the
paper you know like tracing the the
movement of the planets and stuff I got
a what do you
call an ulcer on my tip of my finger
like a open loon from trying to I wore
my finger out on this calculation for a
year uh some
[Music]
all I was able to do the only benefit I
got out of it was I wore out to s s is a
special wooden board that they use for
doing the astrological calculations it
has lines drawn on it and you see I just
wore out a couple of black words okay
they even those spiritual endeavors
were a waste of time they were business
okay it didn't help my practice at
all you don't even get any good seeds
from that okay like some practices they
don't have an immediate result but you
get some kind of seed he said I didn't
even get any seed from that okay
[Music]
don't be the kind of person who goes out
to a sugar cane what do you call a stock
of sugar can and tries to eat the leaves
you know break it open and eat the
inside that's where the what do you call
that's where the sugar is don't waste
your time on peripheral peripherally
interesting spiritual stuff some of
today gave me a book okay this morning
somebody gave me a book they said oh
you're going to love it guessing Michael
I said what is it they said you know
this neuroscientist neuro is it neuros
neuroscientist has has figured out that
Buddhism is okay you know and uh you
know I thank them and then I just threw
it you know I mean I just threw it as
soon as I got home I just threw it I I
didn't I opened one page I threw it away
you know it's not going to help you it's
just some guy speculation about
Buddhists are okay now you know and it
doesn't mean anything it's peripheral
spiritual junk just you don't have time
for that okay let's call it let's call
duni let's define it as peripheral
spiritual junk okay you don't have time
go for
the mar right go for the what do you
call it jug go for the spiritual jugular
you know learn to meditate deeply and go
to emptiness and don't waste your time
on New Age stop
okay
[Music]
uh there are people who spend their
entire lives on minor scholar elastic
points or or peripheral spiritual junk
okay and they get old they become what
do you call it Geno means
uh gen means uh see now physically what
do you call
that
what their bodies get used up like
they're
infirm they they're walking like this
they're old they're years old and they
have wasted their life on this new age
jump you know and they know nothing and
they have no accomplishments and they
don't understand anything and they just
got old okay and they wasted their whole
life on that okay we had it in Sedona
right near where I live there's bunch of
places like that
okay and you still see them it's a sad
thing you see these hippies where I live
ex hippies they're like 70 Now 60 years
old and uh in the local food market tiny
food market if I ride my bike it's like
a a long dve you know uh it's half a
wine half the section is half the store
is wine different kinds of wine so these
people who started out their life in the
hippie movement and they were all what
do you call
it inspired to hirer things you know now
they're just like hanging out in the
store and drinking wine you know
and he says and he
says it's pitiful to see a person who
started out with high spiritual
aspirations they wasted their time on
peripheral unauthentic stuff and now
they're sitting at that local store
drinking wine on day and he says n he
says he says it's so sad to see it's sad
to see okay it's really then he says
they're they are old and they're just
trying to get a little physical comfort
from the wine and that's all that's left
with their life that's all they have
left of their life is to sit and talk
about about the old days and have a wine
and he says N N means a say
a a means breaks my heart to see it
I they they started out with such hope
in the 60s you know whatever and now
they're sitting around talking about all
times and drinking
wine and then they didn't do anything
between they didn't gain anything right
they don't have any
real what do you
call strength spiritual strength they
didn't get anything all that
[Music]
time there was a Sutra I'm getting there
okay you're almost home
sorry
uh we not far uh
there was a Sutra named uh you know
usually a Sutra is named by the person
who requested it right like somebody
went up to Lord Buddha and said what do
you think about this and if his name was
Joe then it's called the Sut requested
by Joe okay so there's a suture
requested by uh surata somebody named
surata okay and he was a beggar okay he
was a
beggar the the beggar surata he found a
chami what's a chamani
money or money huh it's a wish giving do
it's like an Aladin lamp Okay if you rub
it you can get anything you want you
just ask it and you get anything you
want I have a bunch of good jokes about
atad lamp from the diamond industry but
I can't tell you uh they're really funny
though any guys I can tell you um so
anyway he found uh a wish giving Jewel
that they will give you anything you
want you just ask this Jewel and
anything you want pop up
he wanted to give it to the most needy
person in the Kingdom okay he decided I
will search the whole Kingdom for the
person who is the poest so he gave it to
P was the king he was the king of the
kingdom and and so this beggar went to
and said look I've been looking for the
most miserable person in the whole
Kingdom and that's you okay and I'm
offering you this jeel I'm not using up
the three wishes I'm giving it to you
okay cuz you are the the saddest person
in this whole Kingdom and and the King
said
why you are the poorest person in this
Kingdom because you have the most desire
of anybody in this Kingdom got it you
are the biggest poer in this Kingdom
because your wants are so are so
fantastic your desires are so unfillable
desire which makes you the poorest
person in this Kingdom
[Music]
then told a story about somebody named G
Ben okay that's not Ben
gami so G has been a title for a
thousand years right and Ben was a
famous uh G of the old days his full
name
is G Ben G okay anyway he was going on
something
happened oh there was a report that uh a
big uh group of Bandits was coming to a
certain place of the bent okay and then
everybody got scared and started
cleaning out their stuff and packing it
and putting it into what do you call Yak
cards and you know and you know the
whole the whole city was loading Yak
carts and and taking stuff out of the to
hide it in the countryside which also
happened before the Communist invasion
in 1959 I mean thousands and thousands
of books were buried thousands of
statues were buried you know some people
were loading up big hearts and and
taking them out of the city and then
gashi Ben picked up his monks of a bull
and he put on his Mug's
sha and he
left cuz that's all he had to think
about that's all he needed got it so he
says you should be like g b
like the only stuff you need you should
be able to take in your hand and walk
out of the city got it that should be
[Music]
okay we're almost I think almost done
I yeah you got like five more
minutes that's almost done time God all
right
Pony we're up to the last one I think it
was getting rid of lots of useless
thoughts like w right am I right you
better say yes you can't get home okay
this is only the first night of 10 years
[Music]
okay try to stop sometimes and think
about how wanting so much stuff that's
the cell phone uh it's probably one of
my
stuff think about how wanting so much
stuff
uh causes problems
[Laughter]
all right I'll answer
it
enough
okay so try to remember how everything
is passing okay your life is passing
right whatever you're interested in now
that's stopping you from
meditating right whatever thing you're
engaged in that is preventing you from
meditating it will pass and you won't
remember it you know whatever you're
working on a new house or you're working
for a new car or you're working for a
new boy or you know whatever it is
you're working for that's leaves you too
busy to meditate for an hour every
day you won't remember it 5 years from
now you know you won't have it a year
from now but 5 years from now you won't
even remember it okay so all those
things are just what do you call it
trans transitory they're just they're
all going to leave you all the all the
stuff you're worried about that keeps
you awake it's not going to exist in 5
years and then you still won't be able
to meditate okay so just leave it and
and and and learn to meditate cuz that
will stay with you and that's a valuable
thing to have and a car is not and a
house is not and most of your
friendships are not okay you learn to
meditate and you have a real valuable
thing okay that will help everybody
[Music]
okay okay here's the punchline and you
get to go home this is a very famous
quotation I'm not sure I agree with
it we have covered the prerequisites for
meditation okay we have covered all the
stuff you should get ready before you
sit down right this whole night this
whole evening we we covered all the
stuff you should get ready for your
meditation before you start to meditate
okay
uh sheep if you get them all together if
you get to a point where you have all
that stuff you need you've got a good
place you got good meditation what
hardcore heavyweight meditation buddies
like bikers heavy big bikers you know
and you got you've got the quiet place
to stay and you've got honestly
acquired housing and food and everything
set okay if you got and you're keeping
your morality right and everything is
set
okay now if you make effort in trying to
learn now if you really bust ass to
meditate okay if you really work hard to
meditate she
means you will achieve sh within six
months
okay it's very famous it's very famous
uh I don't know because maybe nobody I
know has ever assembled all those
conditions right right everybody says I
didn't get to shant in 6 months and then
if you question them you'll find out
they're trying to meditate in a noisy
place or
they didn't clean up their taxes or
there there's something in their life
that they didn't clean up
or they didn't get the instructions
ready or they're missing something out
of these things okay
so spend some time tomorrow think
[Music]
about think
about do you do you have these
prerequisites and what do you need to do
to get them okay what what do you what
is it that you lack before you sit down
to medit okay we will not go through
this Pages again in 10 years we will not
repeat these pages okay you have to keep
up it's like in school when you're doing
math and and you don't do what do you
call
it you don't do geometry and you try to
go on algebra or something and it's not
going to work okay you every time we
have a class you're going to have to
work on it a bit and because you won't
have time next class cuz we'll be on to
something else so in between tonight and
tomorrow afternoon God knows when uh
think about do you have all the stuff
ready to start your meditation practice
and and study these and think them over
okay it'll be online right the this
class will be online
right yeah yeah so if you need the link
talk to Jim but but you can look at the
whole class again or or you can listen
to an audio again but get it straight
and then and then examine your life and
see if you have everything you need to
start your meditation if you do maybe 6
months is possible if you don't then
maybe it's never going to happen maybe
what you've been doing wrong is not in
your style of meditation maybe it's in
the what do you call it in the
prerequisite State maybe there's
something about the conditions that
you're not you don't have together and
and so look over those conditions and
see what you have and what you don't
have and maybe that's what's holding you
back back maybe it's not that you're not
meditating long enough or you know maybe
it has nothing to do with your style or
your Technique maybe it has to do with
uh something wrong with the place or
something got
it if you're notd you get to go
home okay all right